<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://www.highlevelbits.com/</id>
  <title>atom feed</title>
  <updated>2013-08-12T14:07:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/atom.xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Fredrik &amp; Hardy</name>
    <uri>http://www.highlevelbits.com</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-08-12:/2013/08/italian_infrastructure.html</id>
    <title type="html">infrastructure shots</title>
    <published>2013-08-12T14:07:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-08-12T14:07:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/08/italian_infrastructure.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were fortunate enough to spend a couple of weeks in Italy. A great country always worth returning to. I read a book during the vacation about how Italy managed to become one. Seems like it was mostly a piedmontesian project when it started. Most of Italy were not that keen on the idea. Somehow they managed to pull it through but it is good to keep in mind that the different country parts have very different background, history and culture. Even the food changes a lot as you travel around. We focused on northern italy this time. We decided to go about by train and stayed in 4 cities during our trip. In this post I will show some nice shots of infrastructure (in a broad meaning) I took during the trip. Lets start in Milan with a &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9374266046/"&gt;nice old tram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7324/9374266046_980a707e2e_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a &lt;a href="www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9376268864"&gt;strong moon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2879/9376268864_440e3dd733_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Milan we moved on for some sun and waves at the nice little town &lt;a href="http://www.comune.sestri-levante.ge.it/"&gt;Sestri Levante&lt;/a&gt; about an hour from Genoa. Built on a former island &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9469229505"&gt;narrowly corrected&lt;/a&gt; with the mainland it was a nice place for a amateur photographer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/9469229505_b921f1f9e1_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had some good timing with the sun that produced this &lt;a href="www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9472019882"&gt;awesome view&lt;/a&gt; one of the evenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/9472019882_eebc3586ed_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We moved on to Genoa (or Genova as the locals spell it). This former mechant republic used to compete with Venice on the high seas. Contrary to Venice it still is one of the important ports in Italy. We took a walk down to the 500 year old lighthouse for some &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9471054149"&gt;views of the modern harbor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/9471054149_dfe7864733_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genoa is built where the mountains meet the mediterranean so there is a &lt;a href="www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9471062411"&gt;need for tunnels&lt;/a&gt;. One of my best shots during the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5499/9471062411_78b6535c78_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Genoa we continued to Bologna via Cinque Terre. It rained to we couldn’t explore the 5 villages by the sea properly. But you’ll get &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9477777932"&gt;the idea&lt;/a&gt; anyway…..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2832/9477777932_651841f59d_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9477788986"&gt;another tunnel&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2855/9477788986_de2afcf87a_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bologna is an awesome city. Despite being old and like an old museum it still is lively. Likely due to its very old university still going strong. Much of the streets in the inner city got colonnades which us just an &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9487213376"&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/9484436291"&gt;thing&lt;/a&gt; to have in a city. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5449/9487213376_7c771e8e84_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;
&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2819/9484436291_3428fb4370_c.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Bologna we turned north and spend a couple of days in Innsbruck and München on our way home. All in all a good trip. All the &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/"&gt;pictures from the trip&lt;/a&gt; can be found at flickr.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-08-09:/2013/08/freedom.html</id>
    <title type="html">freedom</title>
    <published>2013-08-08T23:07:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-08-08T23:07:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/08/freedom.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jollino/5736137535"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2182/5736137535_dee0bcbd61.jpg" style="float:right" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I need to write a little piece on freedom. Recent affairs regarding surveillance carried out by a huge democracy and self proclaimed defender of freedom has made me think. No new splendid thoughts - just a reminder of some important things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a distant past the Internet was a place where anyone could share information using open standards. The infrastructure of the internet creates a place where information is published and interchanged at will but controlled by the user. Lets call this the &lt;strong&gt;personal internet&lt;/strong&gt;. As the personal internet grew and proved useful for the masses so did the business value of having a corporate presence on the internet. This shift started to happen about 15 years ago and is probably not complete yet. Lets call this the &lt;strong&gt;corporate internet&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate internet is made up of many different business interests. There are &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; companies that increasingly do their business using the web. Different industries have reached different levels of maturity. Some industries have embraced the net fully and do most of their business netwise while other industries are more physical in nature and so will only use the web for parts of their business anyway. Then there are new companies that have as their sole business idea to do things on the web. Some of them has grown rather big and are now full blown multinational corporations with all that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that data communications always has been monitored by government agencies but the shift towards the corporate internet surely has made it harder to control for the individual. We all give away much of our data and our interactions to big players like facebook, apple and google. And these companies do not use open standards for these interchanges. If you want to communicate with a facebook user you are doomed to be a facebook user yourself. Far from the open and highly distributed mechanisms of email for example. (Or news if anyone remembers?) And most of us just don’t care at all. Convenience makes it so easy compared to freer alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sidenote: yes I am aware that facebook uses open standards like HTTP and HTML to communicate with its users. The point here is that they are not using an open standard for the communication between users.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nolifebeforecoffee/124659356"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/1/124659356_bbe1e5b661.jpg" style="float:left" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In comes surveillance. As soon as we give away the infrastructure of our interactions to business interests we also give away the control over access to those interactions. Suddenly it is someone else’s corporate decision whether to give away my information to a government agency or not. In the old world it used to be a court order that could enforce surveillance. Sure - the web of open standards can also easily be compromised by whomever wants to listen in. Me for one don’t care much about that since nothing I write is sensitive in any way. It is a matter of principles. I shouldn’t be afraid to say &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; anywhere on the internet. The authorities should not listen in. It reduces my freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all - we really need to &lt;em&gt;abandon&lt;/em&gt; social networks and internet companies that are not using open standards for communication. We should be able to use whatever software we like to interact with each other. The &lt;em&gt;corporate internet&lt;/em&gt; needs to be controlled by the standards of the &lt;em&gt;personal internet&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t let them reduce our freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; Start today by looking at &lt;a href="https://prism-break.org/"&gt;this list of alternative solutions&lt;/a&gt; and start using the thing that hurts the least. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And yes - I am a pharisee writing this on my Apple computer. And I will probably post it on one or several proprietary social networks. Sorry about that…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those great photos are in the open domain under nice licenses for non-commercial use. The chess board photo is by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jollino/"&gt;Daniele Nicolucci&lt;/a&gt; and the surveillance one is by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nolifebeforecoffee/"&gt;nolifebeforecoffee&lt;/a&gt;. Flickr users that use flattr gets one from me whenever I favorite a photo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-06-05:/2013/06/css_sibling.html</id>
    <title type="html">css sibling operator (folding divs)</title>
    <published>2013-06-05T01:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-06-05T01:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/06/css_sibling.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been fiddling with CSS a lot in my current client project. I am no ninja yet but I am getting hold of the elementary stuff at least. Today I made one radio button show a div and another one hide it. To be able to do this you need to know about the sibling operator &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; that is used to find an element matching the selector that is &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the main rule. Consider this markup snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;input checked="checked" class="fold_open" type="radio" value="open" /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;input class="fold_closed" type="radio" value="closed" /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;div class="foldee"&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!-- some awesome markup here --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two radio buttons with classes &lt;code&gt;fold_open&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;fold_closed&lt;/code&gt; respectively. One div with the class &lt;code&gt;foldee&lt;/code&gt;. To make the div fold when &lt;code&gt;fold_closed&lt;/code&gt; selected and unfold when &lt;code&gt;fold_open&lt;/code&gt; is selected - add this css:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.fold_open:checked ~ .foldee {
  display: block;
}

.fold_closed:checked ~ .foldee {
  display: none;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/henry-gail/2844798054"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3221/2844798054_37bc48f208_m.jpg" style="float:right" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This means that when the class &lt;code&gt;fold_open&lt;/code&gt; is checked (works for radio buttons and check boxes) its sibling &lt;code&gt;foldee&lt;/code&gt; will be shown and when &lt;code&gt;fold_closed&lt;/code&gt; is checked it will disappear. A tricky thing with the sibling selector is that it only finds elements after its left hand operator. So if you want to hide something above you will have to rearrange your markup and use inspired styling to make it show up in the right place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will probably not work in &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; browsers mayhaps causing a problem depending on your use case and your user base. For a version that is guaranteed to work you will have to write some scripts instead. The amount of code with something like jquery is about the same. But I found it a bit more elegant to do it with css.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The car in the photo is an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfa_Romeo_1900"&gt;Alfa Romeo 1900 CSS&lt;/a&gt; and it is just here for looks. Find a good photo about css….. It was shot by flickr user Henry Figueroa.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-06-03:/2013/06/pirate_cinema.html</id>
    <title type="html">pirate cinema</title>
    <published>2013-06-03T19:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-06-03T19:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/06/pirate_cinema.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/joi/549393610"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1350/549393610_f6119e19fc_m.jpg" style="float:left" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So I just finished &lt;a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13539171-pirate-cinema"&gt;Pirate Cinema&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://craphound.com/"&gt;Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;. A thought provoking quick read.  It is set in a not so distant future where things have gone a little bit more out of hand. In particular the media lobby has succeeded in adding some invasive legislation in the copyright land. So in this future your internet can be turned off if you illegally download copyrighted content. The main character - 16 year old Trent - manages to get his families internet turned off and then runs of to London for some serious squatting and the important fight for reasonable legislation. It turns out fine in some ways - in other ways not so good. Highlights are the improvised cinema in a cemetery where films are projected from trees onto the wall of a chapel, another highlight are mosquito zappers - a kind of hat with built in mosquito zapping lasers. The attention to technical detail is really fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This novel is a good solid voice in frightening times where our creative freedom is at stake. Lets hope our ending is a bit better than the setting of Pirate Cinema. This was my first encounter with Cory Doctorow and I certainly will try to read more of his work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final word to legislators out there - try to make this world a fun place to live in. Of course - artists should get what they are due - but corporations making a profit out of limiting our creativity should just go away.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-05-21:/2013/05/agila_sverige.html</id>
    <title type="html">agila sverige 2013</title>
    <published>2013-05-21T21:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-05-21T21:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/05/agila_sverige.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was time for my second &lt;a href="http://www.agilasverige.se"&gt;agila sverige&lt;/a&gt;. I attended three years ago and wrote &lt;a href="highlevelbits.com/2010/05/agila-sverige-reflections.html‎"&gt;a couple&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="www.highlevelbits.com/2010/05/agila-sverige-day-2-refelections.html‎"&gt;of reports&lt;/a&gt; so I will try to do something similar this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A difference this year was finding me on the speakers list. My talk was about not writing too much dry code and it went very well. I got very nice and insightful comments afterwards so I am happy about it. &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/aigle_dore/5951683083"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6123/5951683083_7f15fe4bba.jpg" style="float:left" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It was some time since I did this kind of public speaking so I was a bit nervous. But as always I got comments on how calm I seemed. I am apparently good at hiding my nervousness. I definitely need to do this more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A theme that hasn’t gone away since the last time I attended is the reorientation of &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; roles in the new agile world. The old way of thinking in roles seems to be hard to get rid of. This year I sense that the focus on management has faded a bit. Maybe the roles &lt;em&gt;product owner&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;scrum master&lt;/em&gt; has settled a bit? I heard other say the opposite so maybe I just avoided those sessions. Talking about testing prevails as before but it seems like test automation (and automation overall) is more of a given now. A definite trend is the need to talk about requirements gathering. I suspect that teams that has been doing agile for a while have a clear sense of lacking overview images/sketches/diagrams of their system. On the other hand what does &lt;em&gt;doing agile&lt;/em&gt; even mean these days….?!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some talks worthy of mention (that would be all talks but then this post would be sooooo long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.impactmapping.org/"&gt;Impact mapping&lt;/a&gt; was one of the new things for me. &lt;a href="http://blog.staffannoteberg.com/"&gt;Staffan Nöteberg&lt;/a&gt; kicked of the conference by using it to explain how to avoid expensive no-result projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.crisp.se/author/peterantman"&gt;Peter Antman&lt;/a&gt; talked about &lt;a href="http://blog.crisp.se/2013/05/20/peterantman/software-development-and-tragedy-of-the-commons"&gt;code ownership and the tragedy of the commons&lt;/a&gt;. Stuffed with references to high knowledge he ended with a list of things that can make &lt;em&gt;commons&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One entire talk in rhyme by &lt;a href="http://www.marcusoft.net/"&gt;Marcus Hammarberg&lt;/a&gt; about always failing when introducing an agile way of working in large organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/m8rt"&gt;Martin Christensen&lt;/a&gt; had an improved version of the user story format that looked really nice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jimmyjanlen.wordpress.com/"&gt;Jimmy Janlén&lt;/a&gt; alias the evil coach made a great performance about how to continue &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; practices in the name of agile. Very entertaining.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to shave that yak &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bdearth/4881180471"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4081/4881180471_3628d6b4ff_m.jpg" style="float:right" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was explained in a humorous yet thought provoking way by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gabriel_f"&gt;Gabriel Falkenberg&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;It might become hairy!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://agical.se/"&gt;agical crew&lt;/a&gt; represented by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/villesv"&gt;Ville Svärd&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tobbeanderberg"&gt;Tobbe Anderberg&lt;/a&gt; presented &lt;a href="http://mobprogramming.org/"&gt;mob programming&lt;/a&gt;. Sort of pair programming taken one huge step further. The idea is to let the whole team program together on one (1) computer. This is truly innovative and may actually be a good thing to do. The increase in quality will be huge, the learning curve of team members drastically improved not to mention the happiness. Will it be more productive than the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; way? Hard to tell. Maybe not but the increase in quality may well be worth it anyway. I hope I will be able to try it soonish in some setting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/andreas_larsson"&gt;Andreas Larsson&lt;/a&gt; declared the end of &lt;a href="http://theagilerevolution.com/"&gt;the agile revolution&lt;/a&gt; and prompted us to start reigning. There are no true opponents of agile left. We all like it! I wonder if this is because it has been watered out over the years or are we truly changing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ending lightning talk was an amazing performance by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamkillander"&gt;Adam Killander&lt;/a&gt; where he acted out a developer that had to choose between new development and maintenance. In the end he was preaching fundamentalist maintenance to the masses. Check it out in &lt;a href="https://agilasverige.solidtango.com"&gt;them streams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to talks there were a bunch of open spaces of which I only attended five due to cloning incapabilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to write requirements. I went to this one mostly to hear how we talk about this nowadays. I found that not much has changed but there are people executing their specs (cucumber sorta) - that was nice to hear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About getting stuck in technical decisions. We often decide what technical solution to choose based on what we user before, what skill set we have or what seems to be the common choice at the moment rather than base on what technology best suits the problem at hand. One example of this is how we user object oriented techniques to build web sites - a very functional problem space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mob programming talk extended into a very creative open space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About competence. Andreas Larsson showed how he divides competence into the three sub parts technical, domain and personality. An interesting discussion around this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The final one was about (and with) senior developers. Why are they not in abundance? Why do many move on to other roles? How sad is it that we are losing a fair bit of knowledge in this way? Thought provoking and yet another reminder to stay in continuous learning mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some obligatory ending comments about &lt;a href="http://meetingroom.se/"&gt;the venue&lt;/a&gt;. This one works better than the old one. The two rooms used for the two tracks are next to each other so it is easy to change between in the 2 minute breaks. The food has been good and coffee has been available in abundance. The dinner was served in the main conference room which made it all stick together nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with sorta a retrospective. Post-its on the wall and on the chest and some mingling talking about experiences from the conference. Great to just talk about how great it was for a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge amounts of thanks to the organizers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
