<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://www.highlevelbits.com/</id>
  <title>rss feed</title>
  <updated>2013-09-28T13:02:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/rss.xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Fredrik &amp; Hardy</name>
    <uri>http://www.highlevelbits.com</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-09-28:/2013/09/golang_templating_engine.html</id>
    <title type="html">go templating - the basics</title>
    <published>2013-09-28T13:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-28T13:02:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/09/golang_templating_engine.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/29363671@N08/4264734398"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2723/4264734398_f89371801a.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am busy coding a web site with &lt;a href="http://golang.org/"&gt;go&lt;/a&gt;. I am still not convinced that go is the best choice for web development unless performance is in high demand. It is still great fun to learn a new language and a language that have different opinions on many things compared to other languages. This kind of experiences are very good to move forward as a developer. So kudos to &lt;a href="http://www.flatwallet.se/"&gt;flatwallet&lt;/a&gt; that lets me learn go while getting paid for it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We try to use as much as possible of the standard library but sometimes it is hard as I &lt;a href="http://highlevelbits.com/2013/09/pragmatic_unit_testing_with_go.html"&gt;described in my post about testing&lt;/a&gt;. When it comes to web development there is a good enough &lt;a href="http://golang.org/pkg/text/template/"&gt;template engine&lt;/a&gt; that provides with the simplest things to get stuff into your &lt;a href="http://highlevelbits.com/2012/04/control-your-markup.html"&gt;markup&lt;/a&gt;. In mainstream template engines the normal way to get behavior into your template is to use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;% %&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; for executing some code and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%= %&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; for getting some stuff inserted into the generated markup. In go you use double curly braces instead. So in order to insert a value you go &lt;code&gt;{{.Value}}&lt;/code&gt;. The single point is a reference to the data structure (remember - no objects in go) that was passed to the template from the back end code and value is a field in that structure. There is the basic control flow things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{ if .IsActive }}
  Active
{{ else }}
  Inactive
{{ end }}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and loops:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{ range .Books }}
  &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
    {{ .Title }} by {{ .Author }}
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
{{ end }}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using &lt;code&gt;range&lt;/code&gt; the &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; context is set to the current item for each loop over the collection. As you see you just mix curly braces with HTML freely. (So that it looks really messy to the eye….) Since the templating doesn’t conflict with the markup you can also use them in attribute values. This may look nasty at times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div class="{{if .IsActive}}active{{else}}passive{{end}}"/&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to my liking. The alternative is to add another field to the page structure and calculate the value in the go code instead. It adds a bit of duplication and the number of line increases and I am not sure the overall readability goes up. So the above may actually be a good choice at times. In this particular case it has the benefit of keepin css classes in the markup. Indeed - you could do it like this just as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{ if .IsActive }}
  &amp;lt;div class="active"/&amp;gt;
{{ else }}
  &amp;lt;div class="passive"/&amp;gt;
{{ end }}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better or worse? This is a simple div with nothing else in it but consider a real world situation where there are some content inside etc. Then it may be better to go with the compact solution instead. Things like these may be good to put in the coding guidelines for a project. (You all do them - right?!?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can define a template with &lt;code&gt;{{ define "my_template" }} &amp;lt;html&amp;gt;....&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt; {{ end }}&lt;/code&gt; for both whole pages and parts in a page. Say you define a header partial: &lt;code&gt;{{ define "header" }}&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;Menus and other header stuffs.&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;{{ end }}&lt;/code&gt; then you can use it in another template with: &lt;code&gt;{{ template "header" }}&lt;/code&gt;. So that is kind of neat. There is no support for layouts so for solving that in the standard library way you’ll have to do it yourself with functions calling different templates in different contexts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing. You can use &lt;code&gt;with&lt;/code&gt; to get deeper in the context of the page. Like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{ range .Books }}
  &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
    {{ .Title }} by 
    {{ with .Author }}
      {{ .FirstName }}{{ .LastName }}
    {{ end }}
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
{{ end }}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t used this much but it has the benefit of getting evaluated only if there is something in the referenced value. So it is a combined &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; statement with a scope narrower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is a bunch of built-in functions that makes life a bit easier. The one that has bothered me most is &lt;code&gt;call&lt;/code&gt; that lets you call a function from within the template. But not any function. It must either have been previously tied to the template with calls to &lt;code&gt;Funcs&lt;/code&gt; with a &lt;code&gt;FuncMap&lt;/code&gt; or be in the global namespace. So if you have a nice little function tied to the struct you are exposing to your template you can not use it right away. I find this limiting - the extra code to set it up can just as well be used to introduce another variable in the struct that holds the computed value. You end up with redundant data in your model where parts are ‘real’ data and parts are computed values. I don’t have a perfect &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; for this yet and will come back to review it later and maybe another post about advanced templating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard library documentation is really good. The templating basics is in the &lt;a href="http://golang.org/pkg/text/template/"&gt;text/template package&lt;/a&gt; while there are some added things for web pages in the &lt;a href="http://golang.org/pkg/text/template/"&gt;html/template package&lt;/a&gt;. This separation is obviously good so that you can do templating inside whatever format you work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engine photo by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/29363671@N08/"&gt;Jon Pekelnicky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-09-15:/2013/09/baruco_day_2.html</id>
    <title type="html">baruco day two [conference report]</title>
    <published>2013-09-15T21:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-15T21:02:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/09/baruco_day_2.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://assets2013.baruco.org/assets/logo-3ff2130df4d6cf11e8bd7f1e3d72bb6d.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice organisers thought it wise to start the second day an hour later. Surely a blessing for the first speaker. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keynote by Paolo Perrotta was entertaining and thought provoking. Spanning such wide topics as the discovery of how to calculate longitudes, distant forefathers crawling up from the sea and the horrors of SOAP, Paolo made a good shot at comparing progress in the software discipline with the evolution of mankind and maybe just maybe the future will be more functional than the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the keynote the talks were more technical this day. The future of jruby, rubymotion for iOS coding, a bit of clojure, tender love shaving a yak. That sort of thing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than listing all the talks I will focus on my takeaways from the conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;functional programming is on the move. I heard a lot about that object orientation has become the way to code in the 21st century. But there are some issues that are not solved that well with object orientation. It doesn’t scale nicely and it seems that it is next to impossible to write larger systems with the technique. Functional has some characteristics that makes it attractive for the upcoming challenges. It is highly scalable (due to immutability) and it is really great for testing. THat functional sort of ‘appears’ at a Ruby conference is a good sign that it is up and coming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a sense of fatigue and maturity. Look how far we have come in our field, that is great but many things still suck and we are bit tired. Hopefully a conference like this one can reeenergize and help us move on. The needs for decent software creation will not diminish in neither the close nor the distant future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maybe use jruby in production?!?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there were several talks about the quality without a name. How do we go about producing software that can stay around for a while? Since I have been interested in these things since late 90s I didn’t learn much but it gives me hope that good practices are preached at a conference like this one. How to penetrate the breadth of developers out there is still largely an unknown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up: a really nice conference moulded in the standard format. The communication flows mainly in one direction with breaks and parties making it possible to interact a bit further. This bothers me more and more with conferences - I would prefer a bit more interactivity. This time I sneaked away a bit prematurely feeling numb from all the listening. So sadly I missed the lightning talks - I am sure this was one of the best parts of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily I booked a further two days in Barcelona so now that the conference is over I will find out more about the city. It looks really nice so far! I had good food both nights at random restaurants and I stay at a really &lt;a href="https://sv.airbnb.com/rooms/1159801"&gt;nice airbnb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-09-14:/2013/09/baruco_day_1.html</id>
    <title type="html">baruco day one [conference report]</title>
    <published>2013-09-14T21:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-14T21:02:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/09/baruco_day_1.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://assets2013.baruco.org/assets/logo-3ff2130df4d6cf11e8bd7f1e3d72bb6d.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I went to Ghent and &lt;a href="http://arrrrcamp.be/"&gt;arrrrcamp&lt;/a&gt; but failed to write a report. This year I am improving with reports from both days of &lt;a href="http://www.baruco.org"&gt;baruco&lt;/a&gt; - a bit larger a conference but similar in form to arrrrcamp. The timing could have been better though. I left a rails assignment two weeks ago and are now spending my days coding go. Exciting indeed but my ruby wanderings will be limited to side projects for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference started with a keynote by the creator of &lt;a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/"&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/yukihiro_matz"&gt;Yukihiro Matzumoto&lt;/a&gt; (aka Matz). He started out with talking about himself. How he started coding basic on a very limited device some 30+ years from now and how he started designing Ruby 20 years ago. A very nice personal touch. The most thought provoking thing from the talk was how (computer) languages affect the way we think. Just like natural languages do. The way we have of communicating clearly influences how we organize our thoughts around a certain problem. Later on &lt;a href="http://blog.mattwynne.net/"&gt;Matt Wynne&lt;/a&gt; touched the same issue when giving a short overview over the history of object oriented programming. How it all started with Simula but then around 1980 branched of into Smalltalk and C++ where Smalltalk stands for less control, higher freedom and worse performance and C++ of the opposite. Matt pointed out that UML and the Rational Unified Process conglomerate came out of the C++ community whereas nice things like Domain Driven Design and eXtreme Programming came right out of the Smalltalk community. (No C++ programmers around to defend it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matz also told as a bit about future plans for Ruby core. Ruby 2.1 is due before christmas. Refinements will be a permanent feature of the language then. New releases will appear on an annual basis from now on. Ruby 3.0 in 2023 then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Matz there were two talks about technical stuff relating to scaling Ruby. I haven’t had that kind of problems yet. If I am fortunate enough to build something that needs to scale massively I’ll have to deal with it then. Likely the performant parts will be rewritten in Go rather than trying to get Ruby to perform. Later on another talk on the technical side argued about obvious things like keepin secrets in env variables and trying to have dev and test environments as similar as production as possible. I suspect many needed to hear this so I was happy about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another trait of the first day was several ventures into object orientation. Matt Wynne described how a rewrite of cucumber made it into another kind of object oriented. It sounded very close to functional though so hard to tell the significance. &lt;a href="http://www.sandimetz.com/"&gt;Sandi Metz&lt;/a&gt; gave us a couple of rules for our object oriented life. Things like 100 lines to a class and 5 to a method. Sort of clean code baked down to a few rules. Interesting indeed. I have two rules: (1) write code that is easy to read (2) for the next person working on it. The result is pretty much the same. I don’t care much how these rules are formulated but I want them to exist (written or verbally) in any project I work on. &lt;a href="http://coreyhaines.com/"&gt;Corey Haines&lt;/a&gt; moved in the same hood with his entertaining talk &lt;em&gt;Design Patterns And The Proper Cultivation Thereof&lt;/em&gt; which in summary made the point that design patterns sure are useful if used as they were meant to be. He quoted &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ChristopherAlexander"&gt;Christoper Alexander&lt;/a&gt; (always nice!) saying that the application of design patterns can be done many times but will not produce the same result twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iHiD"&gt;Jeremy Walker&lt;/a&gt; had a really nice talk about productivity. Most of the common sense things came though including work hard but not too hard and spiders on caffeine (which I have seen before - Linda Rising maybe?). The only thing I missed was pomodoro which would fit nicely into the focused work combined with the need for exercise now and then. People argue that you can’t use pomodoro if you want to reach and stay in flow. I don’t agree with that from my own personal experience. But it sure is different to us all and that was one of the important take aways from Jeremy’s talk. In the same spirit - &lt;a href="http://about.avdi.org/"&gt;Avdi Grimm&lt;/a&gt; neatly inter-vowed a bit of meta ruby code with a sincere message about finding the love of programming. A very important message to us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event is nicely organized with above standard foods both for breakfast and lunch. Way to go. Some optimism about the registration process caused a long queue in the morning so the whole day become half an hour late. But we are in Spain now so nemas problemas about that! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended the day with a visit at Nou Camp and saw Barcelona beat Sevilla with 3-2. Lots of energy in that stadium!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-09-08:/2013/09/pragmatic_unit_testing_with_go.html</id>
    <title type="html">pragmatic unit testing with go</title>
    <published>2013-09-08T21:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-08T21:02:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/09/pragmatic_unit_testing_with_go.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ajstarks/8461414333"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8373/8461414333_4a30e15dd3_m.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fortunate to code some &lt;a href="http://golang.org/"&gt;go&lt;/a&gt; at my new assignment. I had some two weeks with the language last fall but apart from that it is new unmarked land for me. It is a nice language that is easy to learn and does things in very different ways. You get started really fast but with that nagging feeling that there is much more to learn around the corner. I suspect that you can be really productive in go. If you like your strong types and a bit lower level than normal you will get back performance only matched by C and a robust piece of code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say - the benefits of unit tests in a strongly typed and opionionated language like go is a bit lower than in dynamic languages like ruby, python and javascript. It is still necessary to keep your code base stable over time. So I have tried it out a bit. I started with the &lt;a href="http://golang.org/pkg/testing/"&gt;standard library approach&lt;/a&gt; where you get something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func TestSomething(t *testing.T) {
  something := false
  if something {
    t.Log("Oh noes - something is false")
    t.Fail()      
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh no. This is a bit verbose for my taste. Some four lines to do an assert…. Sure, you can add some semicolons and get in one line but with reduced readability. I sort of hoped that I had gotten something wrong here. This couldn’t possible be the way to do it? I &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/18637912/135673"&gt;turned to stackoverflow and asked how&lt;/a&gt; to do it. The first two answers pretty much confirmed that this is the way to do it. Idiomatic go according to the language constructors. One of the answers stated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I discourage writing test in the way you seem to have desire for. 
It’s not by chance that the whole stdlib uses the, as you call it, 
“verbose” way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I elaborated my question and asked if it wouldn’t be nice to reuse a bit of code in my own assert method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func AssertTrue(t *testing.T, value bool, message string) {
  if value {
    t.Log(message)
    t.Fail()
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and use it in my test like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func TestSomething(t *testing.T) {
  something := false
  AssertTrue(t, something, "Oh noes - something is false")
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and I got this reply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Based on your update, that is not idiomatic Go. What you are doing is in 
essence designing a test extension framework to mirror what you get in 
the XUnit frameworks. While there is nothing fundamentally wrong, from 
an engineering perspective, it does raise questions as to the value + cost 
of maintaining this extension library. Additionally, you are creating an 
in-house standard that will potentially ruffle feathers. The biggest thing 
about Go is it is not C or Java or C++ or Python and things should be done 
the way the language is constructed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So from this reasoning it seems like normal practices like code reuse is not applicable to go. Weird - me thinks…. So I started to give up hope about this nice little language. Fortunately a third answer (that I accepted) dropped in introducing gocheck and basically telling me that there are other opinions in the go community than the stdlib ones. Good to hear - maybe there is a place for a pragmatic programmer after all. With &lt;a href="http://labix.org/gocheck"&gt;gocheck&lt;/a&gt; you can do asserts easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;func (s *MySuite) TestSomething(c *C) { 
  something := false
  c.Check(something, Equals, true, "Oh noes - something is false") 
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Works for me. I’m gonna use that for a while and see how it feels. I will - however - try to grasp the &lt;em&gt;go way&lt;/em&gt; as I go and if needed will change my mind in this matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect more posts about go during the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-09-04:/2013/09/guardi.html</id>
    <title type="html">guardi - painter of ruins</title>
    <published>2013-09-04T21:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-04T21:02:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/09/guardi.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="http://highlevelbits.com/2013/08/italian_infrastructure.html"&gt;already reported&lt;/a&gt; we spent a couple of weeks in Italy this summer. In Milan we went to Museo Poldi-Pezzoli, once the home of a wealthy family and now turned into a museum with a really nice selecton of paintings. I like these smaller museums. It is possible to view most of the works without getting overwhelmed. This time I fell for a painting by Fransesco Guardi (a new acquaintance for me) called &lt;strong&gt;Architectural Caprice with Roman Ruins&lt;/strong&gt;. The painting shows a ‘normal’ life by the sea and upon that some large roman ruins are added. I liked the sense of how time passes but life goes on and also how the work of the ones before us still dwell among us. The ruins may be seen as a symbol for our history continuously putting its mark on our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The painting can be &lt;a href="http://www.museopoldipezzoli.it/en/node/700"&gt;viewed online&lt;/a&gt; at the museos web site. All rights reserved so can’t be shown here. The following paintings comes from &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org"&gt;wikimedia commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/09/Francesco_Guardi_009.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c7/Francesco_Guardi_008.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
