<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://www.highlevelbits.com/</id>
  <title>rss feed</title>
  <updated>2013-12-15T21:01:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/rss.xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Fredrik &amp; Hardy</name>
    <uri>http://www.highlevelbits.com</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-12-15:/2013/12/simple_backups.html</id>
    <title type="html">simple backups</title>
    <published>2013-12-15T21:01:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-12-15T21:01:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/12/simple_backups.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6054/6261970884_ea884ea79f_b.jpg" alt="backups" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/40133358@N05/6261970884"&gt;Photo by gagam13&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just finished moving a rails thing from &lt;a href="https://heroku.com"&gt;heroku&lt;/a&gt; to my own &lt;a href="https://www.archlinux.org/"&gt;arch linux server&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/"&gt;digital ocean&lt;/a&gt;. This has involved learning lots about server management. Setting up the server with decent security (ufw - uncomplicated firewall to the rescue) and a nginx web service talking to the unicorn-powered rails application. All rather easy and with lots of resources available on the interwebz. I didn’t find much about backing up a postgres database though so I figured something out on my own. And here it is! My requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nightly backups is enough (for now - users may lose latest updates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;backups must be stored on another server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;backups on that other server should be encrypted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves me with 4 tasks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create a backup file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encrypt the backup file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;upload the encrypted file to another server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;schedule a nightly task to initiate the backup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="create-a-backup-file"&gt;Create a backup file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postgres comes with the easy to use &lt;code&gt;pg_dump&lt;/code&gt; command. Name your database and the file you want to export to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;pg_dump -f &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt; &amp;lt;database&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to export all databases in your postgres server you can use the &lt;code&gt;pg_dumpall&lt;/code&gt; command instead and omit the database name. I created a filename with a timestamp so that there will be no file name conflict:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;date +%Y.%m.%d.%H.%M.%S
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;plus a suffix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="encrypt-the-backup-file"&gt;Encrypt the backup file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gnupg&lt;/code&gt; provides with encryption. Easily installed with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;pacman -S gnupg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I settled for symmetric encryption with a hard password. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpg --symmetric --batch --passphrase &amp;lt;password&amp;gt; --force-mdc &amp;lt;backupfile&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;--symmetric&lt;/code&gt; flag says to encrypt symmetrically. This means that we can decrypt with the same password. &lt;code&gt;--batch&lt;/code&gt; makes it possible to pass in the passphrase on the command line rather than getting a prompt to enter it. &lt;code&gt;--force-mdc&lt;/code&gt; makes sure that a warning about mdc is avoided when decrypting. I am not sure what this means. The command creates a file in parallell to the backup file with the added &lt;code&gt;.gpg&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="upload-the-encrypted-file-to-another-server"&gt;Upload the encrypted file to another server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done in many ways. I settled for dropbox mostly because it is free and rather easy to do. Even easier would be something like &lt;code&gt;sftp&lt;/code&gt; if you have the luxury of having another server for backup storing. To communicate with dropbox I use the &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/developers/core"&gt;Core API&lt;/a&gt; with Ruby. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install dropbox-sdk
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use it you need to register an app with dropbox. Then you will get the key and secret needed to initiate communication and get an access token. To get the access token you will need to run the following once:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;require 'dropbox_sdk'

flow = DropboxOAuth2FlowNoRedirect.new(APP_KEY, APP_SECRET)
url = flow.start
puts url
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to the outputted url logged in as the user you want for dropbox and grab the code. Pass it in to the method below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;code = gets.strip
access_token, user_id = flow.finish code 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This access token can then be reused for all subsequent calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then do the actual file transfer with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;client = DropboxClient.new access_token
file = open gpgfilename
response = client.put_file(gpgfilename, file)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the file ends up in the &lt;code&gt;Apps/&amp;lt;yourappname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Ruby here but there are several other options depending on your setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="schedule-a-nightly-task"&gt;Schedule a nightly task&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I put all the above in to one huge ruby file (that I won’t share because it is kinda messy). Then I added it to crontab with &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;export EDITOR=vim
crontab -e
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always fail with vi…. The line to add for a nightly run at 01:37 is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;37 1 * * * /path/to/backup.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that cron executes with &lt;code&gt;/bin/sh&lt;/code&gt; so make sure to test your command under those circumstances. Cron is supposed to send mails when it fails. That remains to set up. I will probably rather hook the job up with nagios once I get that up and running for monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats it for now. I will come back with more server side tips further on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-12-05:/2013/12/arch.html</id>
    <title type="html">finally on linux</title>
    <published>2013-12-05T21:01:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-12-05T21:01:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/12/arch.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.archlinux.org/" style="float:right"&gt;&lt;img src="https://d11xdyzr0div58.cloudfront.net/static/logos/archlinux-logo-dark-90dpi.ebdee92a15b3.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have finally made the step from proprietary software to the free world of linux. I have had to use Windows for many years at several customers but started to used MacOS for my personal things some 6 or 7 years ago. 3 laptops later and it is time to switch again. A gig involving Java is coming up and my almost 3 years old Air is not up for it. Coding Rails and Go has been no problem at all but I fear Java will need some serious powers. So this time I decided to go Linux. The one thing that really made me decide was the NSA findings earlier this year. It is now obvious that closed software can not be trusted to uphold my personal integrity. And it is not that I care that much for my own integrity. I have nothing to hide. It is a matter of principals. Read more about this in my &lt;a href="/2013/08/freedom.html"&gt;freedom rant from august&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Linux it is then but what kind. It seems like the most popular distros are bloated and may give an experience akin to Mac or Windows but I wanted something different and the simplest thing that can possible work. So I got my eyes on &lt;a href="https://www.archlinux.org/"&gt;Arch&lt;/a&gt;. Two fellow hackers, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dahankzter"&gt;Henrik Johansson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jimlar"&gt;Jimmy Larsson&lt;/a&gt; were already on the distro and as I read up on it I decided that this is what I want to use. From &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way"&gt;the arch way&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arch Linux defines simplicity as without unnecessary additions, modifications, or complications, 
and provides a lightweight UNIX-like base structure that allows an individual user to shape the 
system according to their own needs. In short: an elegant, minimalist approach.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A lightweight base structure built with high programming standards will tend to have lower 
system resource demands. The base system is devoid of all clutter that may obscure important 
parts of the system, or make access to them difficult or convoluted. It has a streamlined set of 
succinctly commented, clean configuration files that are arranged for quick access and editing, 
with no cumbersome graphical configuration tools to hide possibilities from the user. An Arch 
Linux system is therefore readily configurable to the very last detail.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complexity without complication.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided on Arch before even buying a piece of hardware. After looking around for a while I settled for a &lt;a href="http://shop.lenovo.com/us/en/laptops/thinkpad/x-series/x230/"&gt;Lenovo ThinkPad X230&lt;/a&gt;. It is small though not as small as the Air. It got the powers and comes with a built-in 3G modem (that I actually got working!). It has a nice keyboard and a track pad that is ok but not as good as the Airs. Keyboard backlight that I finally found out that you can turn on with Fn-Space. (I accidentally lit it when missing a Ctrl-Space sequence trying to complete something in Sublime.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not easy to get started with Linux and Arch is probably even harder. I followed the noob guide to get disks formatted and the distro installed. It took me a couple of hours and I learned a lot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the tricky decision to decide to have a desktop or not. I decided to go simple and avoided KDE and Gnome in favour of a plain window manager - openbox. It does windows and not much more. And when you start using it you soon realize that you don’t really need anything more when you are literate on the comman line. At the moment I have a plain openbox configuration and I run stalonetray for network and battery icons. I also have conky running in default mode with plans to learn how to configure it sometime in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have some things to tweek. Stuff like pdf viewing, file extension management and printing has not been resolved yet. But I haven’t really tried. I will need to get used to replacements for a couple of programs, omnigraffle and iphoto being the most important ones probably. Apart from that it is mostly the same software here as on Apple. I tried with Firefox for a while but it turned out Chromium is better at making all web pages look good. It is likely a font issue with firefox (helvetica) but that is for some other rainy day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now. I will likely be back with more detailed tales of the linux user.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-11-23:/2013/11/post-agile.html</id>
    <title type="html">the postagile world</title>
    <published>2013-11-23T15:01:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-11-23T15:01:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/11/post-agile.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The lines of thoughts in this post started with &lt;a href="http://www.antman.se/"&gt;Peter Antman&lt;/a&gt; inviting to a meeting to discuss a new thing called #notest - a very interesting subject clearly. I felt an urge to rant a bit about this #no trend and thus this tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;the new thing after agile is to put &amp;quot;no&amp;quot; in front of standard practices: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23noestimates&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#noestimates&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23notest&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#notest&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23noprocess&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#noprocess&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23nomanagement&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#nomanagement&lt;/a&gt; but never &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23nocode&amp;amp;src=hash"&gt;#nocode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Fredrik Rubensson (@froderik) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/froderik/statuses/403235228589637632"&gt;November 20, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally when I rant on twitter I get no responses but this time my tweet spawned two separate threads that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/froderik/status/403235228589637632"&gt;merged together after a while&lt;/a&gt;. Both threads questioned that agile is something of the past. And maybe they are right. I don’t know. What I do know is that everyone wants to be agile these days. Agile has won. But at the same time agile has lost its controversy. When I look at the agile manifesto today I just feel that “yeah - this is how I work - this how I react even”. And I am sure many developers feel the same way. The manifesto was hugely important when it came. It summarized a couple of good process oriented movements in 4 points. These 4 things is not much more than common sense really. The reason it was needed was due to the monstrous processes that had grown in strength during the 90s and that threatened to suffocate the entire business. Now agile has been embraced by many. I consulted for a large organisation some years back that claimed to aim for being best in the agile class yet they had no agile practices whatsoever in sight. I then deduced that the word &lt;em&gt;agile&lt;/em&gt; for many had come down to just mean &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. We work in an agile/good way. And no one wants to work in a bad way. Suddenly some of the old &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; practices also makes it into the agile portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nowadays I just want to get things done. If the process stays in the way it has to go. Agile or not.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now live and work in a postagile world. Agile has won and now we have to find out how to improve our work within that mindset. We also need to protect the gains that has been made over the years. Lets have a look at each part of the manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="individuals-and-interactions-over-processes-and-tools"&gt;Individuals and interactions over processes and tools&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The morning meeting and the retrospective has won. Most team work in this way now. We have to beware of getting value out of the morning meeting. In my last team we tried to talk about each thing on the board rather than walk through all the persons. It worked well with a senior team. With a new team it may be better to just go the round. A tight team may decide to skip morning meetings altogether. They are just there to make sure that communication happens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly enough we are more likely to find morning meetings in a team than retrospectives. The tool for continuous improvement that takes place outside the daily loop is of course very important to get anywhere. In the postagile world we need to make sure that we don’t miss out on retrospectives and the opportunity to improve our process continuously. We also need to guard against the agenda of tool vendors. I recently heard that one of my old clients were about to implement a planning to tool to help them with their agile process. Sigh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="working-software-over-comprehensive-documentation"&gt;Working software over comprehensive documentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen one case where a scrum-by-the-book team ended up with no documentation at all. I was asked to do an architectural review and the only material to use was source code and tickets. That was fun! In a postagile world we need to produce the artifacts that is needed. This will always be mostly source code but occasionally we will need to write a couple of documents. These documents are likely to be system overviews. How does things fit together. I like to think of &lt;a href="http://highlevelbits.com/2009/05/software-development-as-mapping.html"&gt;this need as maps&lt;/a&gt;. Maps to help navigate the system and the surrounding world of users and other systems. This metaphor works much better than architecture for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="customer-collaboration-over-contract-negotiation"&gt;Customer collaboration over contract negotiation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This really is about trust. If there is no trust between the customer and me I am lost anyway. It probably is scary as hell to buy custom software since so many projects still fail so badly regardless if they are based on customer collaboration or not. In a postagile world we need to give and receieve trust and we need to educate our customers in demanding visible deliverables continuously. Still many teams are reluctant to deliver things soon and many customers don’t want to get that involved. That need to change. Customers must involve themselves in the delivery rythm of their software team and the team need to be verbose about their progress and more importantly about their obstacles. There will be no true dialog about a piece of software until it is there to look at and use. It happpens all the time that the first time there is any real feedback is when the piece is in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="responding-to-change-over-following-a-plan"&gt;Responding to change over following a plan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is a bit tricky. While it is normally no point in planning the future many organisations need to manage expectations about the future in some way. Plans for what features will get into future releases may be necessary to keep business. You may see this also as responding to change but it is likely that the business side of things would like to call it a plan. In a postagile world we need to make long term plans that can be abandoned when we respond to change. We need to be good at communicating this dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="what-is-this-postagile-thing-anyway"&gt;What is this postagile thing anyway&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?q=postagile"&gt;Duckduckgoing for postagile&lt;/a&gt; gives a bunch of interesting hits. I guess people started talking about postagile even earlier than the &lt;a href="http://www.infoq.com/news/2007/05/is-post-agile-just-agile"&gt;infoq post from 2007&lt;/a&gt; that asks “Is Post-Agile Just Agile?”. The answer is yes. So the idea of something postagile has been around for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My twitter ranting lead to an interesting dialog with &lt;a href="http://zuill.us/WoodyZuill/"&gt;Woody Zuill&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.jbrains.ca/"&gt;J. B. Rainsberger&lt;/a&gt; to start with and then &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/dahankzter"&gt;Henrik Johansson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/YvesHanoulle"&gt;Yves Hanoulle&lt;/a&gt; joined in. After that I felt the need to rant a bit more in this post. To sum it up - this is what I have found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile is the consensus we have reached. Postagile is the task of improving our work on an agile foundation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-11-13:/2013/11/composers.html</id>
    <title type="html">timeline of composers</title>
    <published>2013-11-13T20:13:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-11-13T20:13:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/11/composers.html"/>
    <content type="html">It is the season of requiems. At least here in Sweden we have lots of
&lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requiem'&gt;
  Requiem
&lt;/a&gt;
concerts around
&lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halloween'&gt;
  Halloween
&lt;/a&gt;
or Alla Helgons Afton as we used to call it before the Americanization began. The triumphal entry of Halloween into Swedish culture may be the subject of another blog post. This blog post is about composers. We have been to two requiems this year. The ones by Duruflé and Brahms. I knew that Duruflé is kind of recent. The requiem is from the 40s. But I tried to put Brahms in the same time as Haydn which turned out to be totally and fundamentally wrong since Haydn was all dead before Brahms was born. So to make some sense out of the when of composers I decided to construct a time line.
&lt;script src="https://www.google.com/jsapi?autoload={'modules':[{'name':'visualization','version':'1','packages':['timeline']}]}" type='text/javascript'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  google.setOnLoadCallback(drawChart);
  
  function drawChart() {
    var container = document.getElementById('composers');
  
    var chart = new google.visualization.Timeline(container);
  
    var dataTable = new google.visualization.DataTable();
  
    dataTable.addColumn({ type: 'string', id: 'Composer' });
    dataTable.addColumn({ type: 'date', id: 'Start' });
    dataTable.addColumn({ type: 'date', id: 'End' });
  
    dataTable.addRows([
      [ 'Händel', new Date(1685, 2, 23), new Date(1759, 4, 14) ],
      [ 'Bach', new Date(1685, 3, 31), new Date(1750, 7, 28) ],
      [ 'Haydn', new Date(1732, 3, 31), new Date(1809, 5, 31) ],
      [ 'Mozart', new Date(1756, 1, 27), new Date(1791, 12, 5) ],
      [ 'Beethoven', new Date(1770, 12, 17), new Date(1827, 3, 26) ],
      [ 'Verdi', new Date(1813, 10, 10), new Date(1901, 1, 27) ],
      [ 'Brahms', new Date(1833, 5, 7), new Date(1897, 4, 3) ],
      [ 'Tchaikovsky', new Date(1840, 5, 7), new Date(1893, 11, 6) ],
      [ 'Grieg', new Date(1843, 6, 15), new Date(1907, 9, 4) ],
      [ 'Fauré', new Date(1845, 5, 12), new Date(1924, 11, 2) ],
      [ 'Puccini', new Date(1858, 12, 22), new Date(1924, 11, 29) ],
      [ 'Debussy', new Date(1862, 8, 22), new Date(1918, 3, 25) ],
      [ 'Ravel', new Date(1875, 3, 7), new Date(1937, 12, 28) ],
      [ 'Stravinsky', new Date(1882, 6, 17), new Date(1971, 4, 16) ],
      [ 'Duruflé', new Date(1902, 1, 11), new Date(1986, 6, 16) ]
    ]);
  
    chart.draw(dataTable);
  }
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class='graph' id='composers' style='height: 700px; width: 100%; margin-top: 20px;'&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I added randomly composers I came to think off and that I like or that are *important*. (Disclaimer: I don't really like Brahms...) For a while there was no living composer between Beethoven and Brahms but than I came to think of Verdi. He saves the continuity through the graph....
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There seems to be a cluster of composers born in the middle of the 19th century and active towards the late 19th century that I particularly like. A favorite for a long time in my youth - maybe because I play the piano - was Claude Debussy. The best piece of classical music I know right now is the Requiem by Gabriel Fauré. Also interesting is that this period is also the most interesting when it comes to visual arts. This is the age of impressionists with great French painters like Monet and Degas leading the way. My favorite Swedish art is also from this time. What was it that made this time so interesting when it comes to the arts? Yet another blog post about that may-haps but I think the answer may be found in the borderlands between absolutism and relativism, authority and freedom etc. It was all falling apart - or in place depending on your view - at this time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  For the nerd. You may look at the source to see what I did. It is a straightforward use of the
  &lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/chart/interactive/docs/gallery/timeline'&gt;
    time line graph
  &lt;/a&gt;
  in the Google visualization API. I have been using some of the other graph types for statistics with my current client so it was an easy choice to put this together with the same technique. And the data was put in by MANUALLY reading wikipedia articles and transporting dates into the code. Will build integration with freebase or similar another time.....
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.highlevelbits.com,2013-11-03:/2013/11/china.html</id>
    <title type="html">visions of china</title>
    <published>2013-11-03T15:01:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-11-03T15:01:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.highlevelbits.com/2013/11/china.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8465/8372395689_1a5a353bc8_b.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like numbers. This is why I often sneak into &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/froderik/"&gt;my flickr account&lt;/a&gt; and look at statistics. I have had an account for almost 8 years and there has beeen som 230000 views of my almost 8500 photos. And the more photos I put up - the more views I get. The other day I got interested in a peak on 30th of october with 1622 views and I found out that a picture (shown above) I took from the dragon tower in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harbin"&gt;Harbin&lt;/a&gt; (China) last christmas had been used in &lt;a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/10/30/5042534/daan-roosegaarde-vacuum-looks-to-sweep-away-china-smog-in-beijing"&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;the verge&lt;/strong&gt; post&lt;/a&gt; about the chinese smog problem. Fun! I really liked the dreamy views from up the tower created by the cold -30 degrees celsius and the coal factories. Cold and cool….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another shot I am happy with is this night time view of the main railway station in Harbin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8354/8373376294_4aac9d57ba_b.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/search/?w=36307913@N00&amp;amp;q=harbin"&gt;more photos&lt;/a&gt; from our days in Harbin including many of ice sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Harbin we got to Beijing by train. We only had two days there but still enough to get a good view of the forbidden palace and the wall. We had some luck with the weather the day when &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/search/?w=36307913@N00&amp;amp;q=great%20wall"&gt;we went out to the wall&lt;/a&gt; - cold and sunny!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8214/8441104536_a18c490d83_b.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our visit to the forbidden palace was in very cloudy weather so no nice pictures from there. Night time in the old parts of Beijing on the other hand is something extra. It is rather dark - not much street lihtning but you still fell safe. Probably because there are much people around. The photo below is from a restaurant street where we had some nice hot pot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8193/8440607785_e90fb36635_b.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more chinese goodness you can browse all &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/search/?w=36307913@N00&amp;amp;q=china"&gt;my photos from China&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
